{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>A member of this family founded the first teaching hospital in Ethiopia and moved to Addis Ababa at Haile Selassie\u2019s invitation. Another member of this family was arrested for slapping a policeman while at a Winston Churchill talk and was named Adela. In an incident known as (+) Black Friday, H.H. Asquith refused to meet a member of this family who had founded the WSPU. The 1918 Representation of the People Act allowed (*) </b> women to vote for the first time, thus accomplishing the goals of, for the points, what family of British suffragettes whose members included Sylvia and Emmeline?", "answer": "<b> Pankhurst</b> family", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Sam Nzima took a famous photograph of this event: a victim being rushed to a clinic with his sister Antoinette Sithole running along. This event led to pamphlets calling for the hanging of B.J. Vorster. During this event, 13 year old Hector Pieterson was shot at</b> <b>Orlando West (+)</b> <b>High School. Prior to this event, Punt Johnson discussed the problem</b> <b>of mediums of instruction in schools. In remembrance of this event, June 16th is now celebrated as Youth Day, commemorating the violent (*) </b> police response to a strike against requirements to speak Afrikaans. For the points, name this 1976 student demonstration in a namesake district of Johannesburg, South Africa.", "answer": "<b> Soweto</b> Uprising", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This process included the development of a type of water clock known as a</b><em><b> wadokei</b></em><b>. The </b><em><b>New Text on Anatomy</b></em><b> was the first major translation that took advantage of this process,</b> <b>which was known natively as (+)</b> <em><b>rangaku</b></em><b>. This process, which was made possible by the</b> <b>allowance of traders on the island of (*)</b> Dejima, allowed its country to understand contemporary scientific progress despite its<em> sakoku</em> isolationist policies. For the points, name this practice by which Tokugawa-era Japan acquired knowledge from traders of a certain European country.", "answer": "<b> Dutch learning</b> (accept<b> Western learning</b>; accept<b> Rangaku</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This composer, who spurned an offer to become Emperor Maximilian II\u2019s music director, worked with Annibale Zoilo on a failed attempt to restore plainchant. This composer\u2019s music formed the basis of Johann (+) Fux\u2019s [fooks\u2019s] codification of species counterpoint in </b><em><b>Gradus ad Parnassum</b></em><b>, and Claudio Monteverdi referred to his style as \u201cprima practica.\u201dOne of his pieces, named after a short-lived (*)</b> pontiff, was the subject of a legend that its clear vocal lines convinced the Council of Trent to not ban polyphony. For the points, name this Renaissance composer of the<em> Pope Marcellus Mass</em>.", "answer": "Giovanni Pierluigi da<b> Palestrina</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Tracking down two men who had killed over twenty workers of this company was the first big break of detective William Burns\u2019s career. The McNamara brothers were convicted</b> <b>of the (+)</b> <b>1910 bombing of this company\u2019s offices. During Harry Chandler\u2019s leadership of</b> <b>this company in the early 20th century, it was party to the (*)</b><em> Bridges</em> case that struck down laws against publishing information about ongoing court cases. Harrison Gray Otis founded the modern incarnation of, for the points, what newspaper based in California\u2019s most populous city?", "answer": "<b> Los Angeles Times</b> (or<b> LA Times</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s son won a battle fought in which his fleet of 200 triremes defeated the forces of Pherendatis and Tithraustes. This man, whose son won the Battle of the Eurymedon River, died of gangrene after attaining a leg wound during the failed siege of (+) Paros. This man, who was from a family of prominent chariot racers, marched to western Attica to force Datis to flee at a battle in which he served as (*)</b><em> strategoi</em>. At that battle, this father of Cimon oversaw the forces of Themistocles and Callimachus. For the points, name this Athenian commander at the Battle of Marathon.", "answer": "<b> Miltiades</b> [mill-TIE-uh-deez] the Younger", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Thomas Cutler wrote a popular history of this battle, which was the last battle covered in Evan Thomas\u2019 book</b><em><b> Sea of Thunder</b></em><b>. Jesse Oldendorf\u2019s forces pulled off the last recorded</b> <b>instance of \u201ccrossing the T\u201d at this battle. The phrase (+)</b> <b>\u201cthe world wonders\u201d was</b> <b>appended to a message sent by Chester Nimitz during this battle after a ruse tricked the commander of the Third Fleet into moving north. (*) </b> Bull Halsey was reprimanded after this battle, where the Special Attack Force carried out the earliest kamikaze attacks. For the points, name this October 1944 battle in the Philippines, arguably the largest naval battle in history.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Leyte</b> Gulf Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>After this state\u2019s electric chair, nicknamed Gruesome Gertie, failed to execute Willie Harris, the Supreme Court ruled in</b><em><b> Francis v. Resweber</b></em><b> that trying again was legal. This state\u2019s primary source of slaves nicknames its Angola prison. A Supreme Court case from this state drew a distinction between (+) \u201cnational citizenship\u201d and \u201cstate citizenship.\u201d The Slaughterhouse Cases arose from this state, where an 1872 gubernatorial election sparked a massacre of African Americans in (*) </b> Colfax. An anti-Semitic Union general was recalled from administering this state\u2019s largest city in December 1862. For the points, name this state where Benjamin Butler briefly ruled occupied New Orleans.", "answer": "<b> Louisiana</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This island employed a \u201cfishing net\u201d approach to capturing foreign investment whose first success came when Royal Little established several Textron factories on this island.</b> <b>From the 1940s to the 1970s, this island experienced a (+)</b> <b>\u201cmiracle\u201d that flipped its</b> <b>economy from agriculture to manufacturing through Operation Bootstrap, which was the brainchild of Rexford Tugwell and (*)</b> Luis Munoz Marin. This island\u2019s current governor, Ricardo Rossello, coordinated relief efforts in September 2017 after its power grid was devastated by Hurricane Maria. For the points, name this Caribbean island that remains an unincorporated territory of the US.", "answer": "<b> Puerto Rico</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s son, a Confederate General, was arrested by William Hardee for drunkenness, and his other son replaced Union commander Daniel Leasure. This man served as aide-de-camp to Isaac Shelby at the Battle of the Thames. With John Rowan, this man helped negotiate the boundary between (+) Tennessee and his home state of Kentucky after issues arose from the surveying of the Walker Line. This man, who served as Attorney General for Millard Fillmore, proposed legislation that (*)</b> would have extended the Missouri Compromise to the Pacific Ocean. \u201cPersonal Liberty Laws\u201d that would have impeded federal fugitive slave laws would have been banned in, for the points, what Kentucky Senator\u2019s namesake compromise?", "answer": "John<b> Crittenden</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>J.H Netteville ran one of these locations, which Ulrich Bonnell Phillips studied. James Battle Avirett wrote about an \u201cold\u201d one of these structures with the urging of Zebulon</b> <b>Baird Vance. Robert Fogel and Stanley Engerman\u2019s (+)</b> <em><b>Time on the Cross</b></em><b> studied these</b> <b>institutions. During the Vicksburg Campaign, General Ulysses Grant spared the destruction of one of these structures owned by the (*) </b> pro-Union Haller Nut. Southern agriculture in the Antebellum Era was defined by, for the points, what large institutional farms where crops like cotton were grown by slaves?", "answer": "<b> plantation</b>s (prompt on generic terms, including \u201cfarm\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This treaty ended a conflict that included the Council of Ten\u2019s execution of Francesco Bussone, Count of Carmagnola, who won the decisive battle of MacLodio. Niccolo Piccinino lost to Florentine forces at the Battle of (+) Anghiari in another conflict that was ended by this treaty. Nicholas V supported this agreement, which created a border at the Adda River and made Francesco (*)</b> Sforza the Duke of Milan. The Italic League was founded a few months after the signing of, for the points, what peace treaty between Milan, Naples, and Florence in April 1454?", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Lodi</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For the points, name this third Ming Dynasty emperor who commissioned the Treasure Voyages of Zheng He.", "answer": "<b> Yongle</b> Emperor (or<b> Zhu Di</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A person partially named for this color imagined himself planting a stick inside a hoop, which turns into a world tree; that man named for this color had a vision of six grandfathers at the age of nine, as related in the third chapter of a book by John Neihardt. A (+) confederacy of Native Americans partially named for this color includes the Piegan peoples and were a traditional enemy of the (*) </b> Crow. A Sioux medicine man was named after an elk of this color. For the points, what color is followed by \u201cfoot\u201d in the name of a Native American nation in the northwestern US?", "answer": "<b> black</b> (accept<b> Black</b> Elk; accept<b> Black</b>foot Confederacy)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A campaign against intellectuals from this demographic gave rise to the term \u201crootless cosmopolitan.\u201d A deputy during the negotiation of the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact was among the thirteen people of this type killed during the \u201cNight of the Murdered Poets.\u201d</b> <b>The book</b><em><b> Stalin\u201ds Last Crime</b></em><b> deals with a conspiracy to frame (+)</b> <b>doctors who were of</b> <b>this demographic. Henry Ford helped publish hundreds of thousands of copies of a forged document describing these peoples\u2019 plans for world domination, the (*)</b><em> Protocols of the Elders</em> <em>of Zion</em>. For the points, name these people who faced much Russian anti-Semitism.", "answer": "Russian<b> Jew</b>s Page 7", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Pedro Aramburu\u2019s corpse was used to pressure the repatriation of this woman\u2019s body, which had been embalmed by Pedro Ara and reburied in Milan. The (+) \u201cCabildo Abierto\u201dwas a rally for this woman, who founded a charitable foundation led by Delia Parodi. A memorial for this woman was held during the 1952 Olympics. This (*)</b> \u201dSpiritual Leader of the Nation\u201d responded to the revelation that George VI would not meet her by skipping Britain in her\u201cRainbow Tour\u201d of Europe. For the points, name this First Lady of Argentina who died of cervical cancer in 1952.", "answer": "<b> E</b>va<b> Per\u00b4on</b> (or<b> Evita</b>; prompt on Per\u00b4on)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. The Senior Citizens Tunnel was created to facilitate this action. An Austin-Healey Sprite with the driver\u2019s mother-in-law in the trunk had its windshield removed so that it could perform this action. In an article by Gordon Rowley, he claims that young men performed this action by flashing their Playboy Club IDs. Harry (+) Deterling performed this action by ramming a train through fortifications, thus reaching Spandau. Peter Liebing captured a picture of Conrad Schumann performing this action by performing a (*)</b> \u201cleap of hope,\u201d and Peter Fechter [fesh-ter] was shot while trying to do it. For the points, name this action performed by people escaping East Germany at places like Checkpoint Charlie.", "answer": "<b> crossing the Berlin Wall</b> (accept descriptions of<b> escaping East Germany</b> before it is read; accept equivalent descriptions; prompt on partial answers like \u201ccrossing a border\u201d) (35) <b>This city\u2019s namesake museum of art includes an installation of an old-fashioned door</b> <b>with a peep hole that shows a nude landscape called</b><em><b>\u00b4</b><b>Etant Donn\u00b4es</b></em><b>, part of its large collection of works by Marcel Duchamp. An 1876 painting set at (+) Jefferson Medical College shows a woman recoiling as the title doctor as he prepares for a surgery; that work was created for a centennial exhibition in this city by an artist who also painted several scenes of (*)</b> rowers and an allegorical depiction of this city\u2019s Schuylkill [school-kill] River. Thomas Eakins painted the Gross Clinic in, for the points, what city home to the Barnes Foundation and Independence Hall? ANSWER:<b> Philadelphia</b> Page 8", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A member of this family was likely assassinated and dumped in the Tiber River due to a relationship with his brother\u2019s wife Sancha of Aragon. Ascanio Sforza accused a member of this family of incest after being asked to agree to a marriage annulment. The \u201cInfans Romanus\u201d was born into this family; his mother may have had an affair with a man named Perotto. Lord (+) Byron described writings from a member of this family to Pietro Bembo as \u201cThe prettiest love letters in the world.\u201d A man in this family was made Duke of (*) </b>Valentinois by King Louis XII; that man\u2019s father once held an orgy in the Vatican. For the points, name this Spanish family whose members included the inspiration for Machiavelli\u2019s<em> The Prince</em>, Cesar\u00b4e.", "answer": "<b> Borgia</b> family", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>James D. Johnston surrendered an ironclad at this battle, while Gabriel Rains helped plant mines before this battle. After this battle, Richard Page was court-martialed for surrendering Fort Morgan. At this battle, a strategy mimicking one used at the Battle</b> <b>of (+)</b> <b>Port Hudson involved lashing many wooden vessels together. During this battle,</b> <b>Franklin Buchanan\u2019s fleet was reduced to just the CSS</b><em><b> Tennessee</b></em><b>. This battle resulted in the (*) </b> closure of the final major Confederate port on the Gulf of Mexico. Occurring in Alabama in 1864, for the points, name this battle in which David Farragut allegedly said, \u201cdamn the torpedoes.\u201d", "answer": "Battle of<b> Mobile</b> Bay", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A move that Edward Gibbon claimed \u201chas never been attempted, and has never been repeated\u201d saw this man plan a maneuver around the Caspian Sea through the mountains</b> <b>in order to surprise the Cumans. The Great (+)</b> <b>Cavalry Raid was planned by this man</b> <b>who helped secure a victory at the Battle of Khalka River with Jebe. At Mohi, this man devised a tactic to create weapons that threw stones at the (*) </b> Hungarian crossbowmen his army faced. This general was listed as one of the \u201cfour dogs of Temujin.\u201d For the points, name brilliant Mongol strategist under Genghis Khan.", "answer": "<b> Subotai</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A man who led this organization after replacing Maxwell Rich had, in his youth killed Ramon Casiano over suspicions of a car robbery. \u201cEddie Eagle\u201d was developed by this group, whose Executive Vice President, Franklin Orth, has supported bans on \u201cSaturday</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Night Specials.\u201d Opponents of this organization were told that only a \u201cclenched fist</b> <b>of truth\u201d could fight off lies in a video. (*)</b> Ambrose Burnside served as the first President of this organization, which today utilizes the Political Victory Fund. For the points, name this American special interest organization that was founded after it was discovered Civil War soldiers had a low chance of hitting targets.", "answer": "<b> National Rifle Association</b> (or<b> NRA</b>) Page 10", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}